I would like to share with you today
أود أن أشارك معكم اليوم
a project that has changed how I approach
مشروعًا غيّر كيف أنهج
and practice architecture:
وأمارس الهندسة المعمارية:
the Fez River Rehabilitation Project.
مشروع إعادة تأهيل نهر فاس.
My hometown of Fez, Morocco,
مدينة منشئي فاس بالمغرب
boasts one of the largest walled medieval cities in the world,
تباهي بأحد أكبر المدن القديمة المسوّرة في العالم،
called the medina, nestled in a river valley.
والمسماة بالمدينة، وتقع في وادٍ نهري.
The entire city is a UNESCO World Heritage Site.
المدينة بأكملها هي موقع تراث عالمي لليونسكو.
Since the 1950s, as the population of the medina grew,
منذ الخمسينات، مع نمو سكان المدينة،
basic urban infrastructure
البنية التحتية الأساسية
such as green open spaces and sewage
كالمساحات الخضراء المفتوحة والصرف الصحي
quickly changed and got highly stressed.
تغيرت بسرعة وأجهدت بشدّة.
One of the biggest casualties of the situation
أحد أكبر ضحايا هذا الوضع
was the Fez River, which bisects the medina in its middle
كان نهر فاس، والذي ينصّف المدينة من وسطها
and has been considered for many centuries
واعتبر لقرون عدّة
as the city's very soul.
روح المدينة.
In fact, one can witness the presence
في الواقع، يمكن للمرء أن يلحظ وجود
of the river's extensive water network
شبكة النهر المائية الممتدة
all throughout the city,
من خلال كل المدينة،
in places such as private and public fountains.
في أماكن كالنوافير العامة والخاصة.
Unfortunately, because of the pollution of the river,
للأسف، بسبب تلوث النهر
it has been covered little by little
تمت تغطيته قليلا قليلا
by concrete slabs since 1952.
بألواح خرسانية منذ 1952.
This process of erasure was coupled
عملية المحو هذه رافقها
with the destruction of many houses
تدمير بيوت عدة
along the river banks
على ضفاف النهر
to be able to make machineries
للسماح للآلات
enter the narrow pedestrian network of the medina.
بالدخول في شبكة المشاة الضيقة في المدينة.
Those urban voids quickly became illegal parking
هذه الفجوات المدنية صارت بسرعة مواقف غير قانونية
or trash yards.
أو ساحات قمامة.
Actually, the state of the river
في الحقيقة، حالة النهر
before entering the medina is pretty healthy.
قبل دخول المدينة صحية جدًا.
Then pollution takes its toll,
ثم يجيء أثر التلوث،
mainly due to untreated sewage
بالأساس بسب الصرف الغير معالج
and chemical dumping from crafts such as tanning.
والمهملات الكيميائية من حرف كالدباغة.
At some point, I couldn't bear
في لحظة معينة، لم أستطع تحمل
the desecration of the river,
تدنيس النهر،
such an important part of my city,
كونه جزء مهمًا من مدينتي،
and I decided to take action,
وقررت العمل،
especially after I heard that the city
خصوصا بعد أن سمعت أن المدينة
received a grant to divert sewage water
استلمت منحة لإبعاد مياه الصرف
and to treat it.
ولمعالجتها.
With clean water, suddenly
بماء نظيف، فجأة،
the uncovering of the river became possible,
أصبح كشف النهر ممكنا،
and with luck and actually a lot of pushing,
وبالحظ والكثير من الدفع،
my partner Takako Tajima and I
أنا وشريكي تاكاكو تاجيما
were commissioned by the city to work with a team of engineers
تفوّضنا من قبل المدينة للعمل مع فريق من المهندسين
to uncover the river.
لكشف النهر.
However, we were sneaky,
ولكننا كنا ماكرين
and we proposed more:
وطلبنا المزيد:
to convert riverbanks into pedestrian pathways,
تحويل ضفاف النهر لمماشي
and then to connect these pathways
وشبك هذه المماشي
back to the city fabric,
مع نسيج المدينة
and finally to convert the urban voids
وأخيرا تحويل الفجوات المدنية
along the riverbanks into public spaces
على ضفاف النهر إلى مساحات عامة
that are lacking in the Medina of Fez.
والتي تنقص مدينة فاس.
I will show you briefly now
سأريكم بسرعة الآن
two of these public spaces.
اثنتين من هذه الساحات.
The first one is the Rcif Plaza,
الأولى هي "الرصيف بلازا"،
which sits actually right on top of the river,
والواقعة فوق النهر بالضبط،
which you can see here in dotted lines.
والذي تستطيعون رؤيته هنا في الخطوط المقطعة.
This plaza used to be a chaotic transportation hub
كانت الساحة سابقا مركز تنقل فوضوي
that actually compromised the urban integrity
انتهك من الكمالية المدنية
of the medina, that has the largest
للمدينة، التي تحوي أكبر
pedestrian network in the world.
شبكة مشاة في العالم.
And right beyond the historic bridge that you can see here,
وخلف الجسر التاريخي الذي ترونه هنا،
right next to the plaza,
بجانب الساحة،
you can see that the river looked like
تستطيعون رؤية أن النهر كان يبدو
a river of trash.
كنهر من القمامة.
Instead, what we proposed is to make
في محل ذلك ما اقترحناه هو جعل
the plaza entirely pedestrian,
الساحة خاصة بالمشاة بالكامل،
to cover it with recycled leather canopies,
تغطيتها بمظلات جلد معاد تدويرها،
and to connect it to the banks of the river.
ووصلها بضفاف النهر.
The second site of intervention
ثاني مواقع التدخل
is also an urban void along the river banks,
هو أيضا فجوة مدنية على ضفاف النهر،
and it used to be an illegal parking,
وكانت موقف سيارات غير قانوني،
and we proposed to transform it
واقترحنا تحويله
into the first playground in the medina.
لأول ساحة لعب في المدينة.
The playground is constructed using recycled tires
الساحة بنيت باستخدام عجلات معاد تدويرها
and also is coupled with a constructed wetland
ويرافقها هور اصطناعي
that not only cleans the water of the river
الذي لا ينظف مياه النهر وحسب
but also retains it when floods occur.
بل يحافظ عليها حين تفوض.
As the project progressed and received several design awards,
مع تطور المشروع وحوزه على عدة جوائز تصميم،
new stakeholders intervened
تدخّل مساهمون جدد
and changed the project goals and design.
وغيروا أهداف المشروع وتصميمه.
The only way for us to be able to bring
الطريقة الوحيدة لنا لإعادة
the main goals of the project ahead
الأهداف الأساسية للمشروع للمقدمة
was for us to do something very unusual
كان أن نفعل أمرا غير اعتيادي
that usually architects don't do.
والذي لا يفعله المعماريون في العادة.
It was for us to take our design ego
كان هو أن نأخذ غرورنا بتصاميمنا
and our sense of authorship
وحسّنا الإبداعي
and put it in the backseat
ورميه جانبا
and to focus mainly on being activists
والتركيز أساسا على كوننا نشطاء
and on trying to coalesce
وعلى محاولة توحيد
all of the agendas of stakeholders
جميع الأجندات لأصحاب المصلحة
and focus on the main goals of the project:
والتركيز على الأهداف الرئيسية للمشروع:
that is, to uncover the river, treat its water,
أي كشف النهر ومعالجة مياهه،
and provide public spaces for all.
وتوفير الساحات العامة للجميع.
We were actually very lucky,
كنا في الواقع محظوظين جدا
and many of those goals happened
والعديد من تلك الأهداف قد تحققت
or are in the process of happening.
أو في طور التحقق.
Like, you can see here in the Rcif Plaza.
مثلا ترون هنا في الرصيف بلازا.
This is how it looked like about six years ago.
هذا كان شكله قبله سنوات.
This is how it looks like today.
هذا هو اليوم.
It's still under construction,
لا زال قيد الإنشاء،
but actually it is heavily used
لكنه مستخدم بكثافة
by the local population.
من قبل السكان المحليين.
And finally, this is how the Rcif Plaza will look like
أخيرا هكذا سيكون شكل الرصيف بلازا
when the project is completed.
عند إنهاء المشروع.
This is the river, covered, used as a trash yard.
هذا هو النهر، مغطى، مستخدم كساحة قمامة.
Then after many years of work,
بعد سنوات من العمل،
the river with clean water, uncovered.
النهر بمياه نظيفة، مكشوف.
And finally, you can see here the river
أخيرا، تستيطعون رؤية النهر هنا
when the project will be completed.
عند إكمال المشروع.
So for sure, the Fez River Rehabilitation
لذا بالتأكيد، إعادة تأهيل نهر فاس
will keep on changing and adapting
ستتغير وتتأقلم
to the sociopolitical landscape of the city,
وفقا للصورة السياسية الاجتماعية للمدينة،
but we strongly believe that by reimagining
لكننا نؤمن بشدة أنه بإعادة تصور
the role and the agency of the architect,
دور وعمل المعماري
we have set up the core idea of the project into motion;
أقمنا الفكرة المحورية للمشروع
that is, to transform the river from sewage
وهي تحويل النهر من مجاري
to public space for all,
لمساحة مفتوحة للكل،
thereby making sure that the city of Fez
وبذلك ضامنين أن مدينة فاس
will remain a living city for its inhabitants
ستبقى حية لسكانها
rather than a mummified heritage.
عوضا عن إرث محنط.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)